A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Correspondence Files of William D. Carmichael FA522
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Correspondence Files of William D. Carmichael
1971-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA522
2.8 Cubic Feet
William D. Carmichael joined the Foundation in 1968 as Representative in the Brazil office, a position he held until 1971. In July of 1971, he was promoted to Head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean. In September of 1977, he was transferred and became Head of the Middle East and Africa office. Dr. Carmichael was promoted to Vice President in charge of the new Developing Countries Program in March of 1981, a position he held until his retirement on September 30, 1989. The collection consists of correspondence files spanning from 1971 to 1989, with a small gap from 1975 through 1976. The files begin with Dr. Carmichael's appointment as head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC) and continue until his retirement in 1989. During this time he also was head of the Middle East and Africa (MEA) office and Vice President of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). The files include correspondence with and memoranda about grantees, including approvals for grant extensions and modifications. Memoranda in the files also discuss issues regarding Foundation policy such as budget review questions and internal affirmative action policy.
(7 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Separated Materials Note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Organizational History
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. Its granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. India and Pakistan were the focus of the initial grants, with a more limited number of grants issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants was initiated for the Near East region later that same year.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs such as Population and International Training and Research, became part of a unified International Division. Following an additional reorganization in 1983, the International Division was eliminated and two program divisions were created—the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and the Developing Countries Program (DCP). During the Foundation reorganization of 1989, the Developing Countries Program was broken down into its regional components, and separate programs were created for individual regions and countries.
Biographical Note
Born on September 5, 1929, Dr. William D. Carmichael received a B.A. in Economics from Yale in 1950. In 1952 he received an M.P.A. in Public and International Affairs and an M.A. in Economics from Princeton University. He received a BLitt from Oxford University in Economics in 1955, and was awarded a PhD in Economics by Princeton in 1959. Between 1962 and 1968, Dr. Carmichael served as Dean of Cornell University's Graduate School of Business and Public Administration.
Dr. Carmichael joined the Foundation in 1968 as Representative in the Brazil office, a position he held until 1971. In July of 1971, he was promoted to Head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean. In September of 1977, he was transferred to and became Head of the Middle East and Africa office. Dr. Carmichael became Vice President in charge of the new Developing Countries Program in March of 1981, a position he held until his retirement on September 30, 1989.
After his retirement Dr. Carmichael served as Executive Director of Soviet Union and Eastern European Programs for the Institute of International Education from 1989 to 1993. Since 1993, he has worked as an independent consultant to foundations, NGOs, and universities.
Arrangement
Records are arranged into one series.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence files spanning from 1971 to 1989, with a small gap from 1975 through 1976. The files begin with Dr. Carmichael's appointment as head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC) and continue through to his retirement in 1989. During this time, he also directed the Middle East and Africa (MEA) office and served as Vice President of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). The files include correspondence with and memoranda about grantees, including approvals for grant extensions and modifications. Memoranda in the files also discuss issues regarding Foundation policy such as budget review questions and internal affirmative action policy.
Related Collections
Other information about the Africa and Middle East (AME) Programs can be found in Program Staff Files, 1965-1976, 1987-1994 (FA503).
Additional information about the Developing Countries Program can be found in the Program Staff Files, 1960-1983. The files were maintained by Elisa Scatena and Richard W. Dye, both of whom reported to Dr. Carmichael as head of DCP. A portion of these files have been transferred to Rockefeller Archive Center as FA528 Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files, 1973-1978.
Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Vice President, Office files of William D. Carmichael, 1968-1989, document his oversight of the administration and program activities of Foundation field offices around the world, and of New York-based program staff responsible for grants in developing countries. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals, conference materials and Board of Trustees meeting files. This collection is available for research at the Rockefeller Archive Center. Please see an Archivist for further assistance.
Ford Foundation
- Chronological Correspondence Files, 1971-1974; 1977-1989; I (Box not specified)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Dr. Carmichael's chronological correspondence files dating from 1971 to 1989, with a two-year gap between 1975 and 1976. The files from October 1981 to 1989 are arranged in yearly increments and then alphabetically by recipient’s last name.
  - 1971 Chron File (1 of 3), Jan-Jun 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1971 Chron File (2 of 3), Jul-Oct 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1971 Chron File (3 of 3), Nov-Dec 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1972 Chron File (1 of 4), Jan-Mar 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1972 Chron File (2 of 4), Apr-Jun 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1972 Chron File (3 of 4), Jul-Sep 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1972 Chron File (4 of 4), Oct-Dec 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1973 Chron File (1 of 4), Jan-Mar 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1973 Chron File (2 of 4), Apr-Jun 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1973 Chron File (3 of 4), Jul-Sep 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1973 Chron File (4 of 4), Oct-Dec 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1974 Chron File (1 of 4), Jan-Mar 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1974 Chron File (2 of 4), Apr-Jun 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1974 Chron File (3 of 4), Jul-Sep 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1974 Chron File (4 of 4), Oct-Dec 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1977 Chron File (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1978 Chron File (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1979 Chron File (1 of 2), Jan-Jul 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1979 Chron File (2 of 2), Aug-Dec 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1980 Chron File (1 of 2), Jan-Jun 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1980 Chron File (2 of 2), Jul-Dec 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1981 Chron File, Jan-Sep 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1981-1982 Chron File (alphabetical) (1 of 4), Oct 1981-Mar 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1982 Chron File (alphabetical) (2 of 4), Apr-Jun 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1982 Chron File (alphabetical) (3 of 4), Jul-Sep 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1982 Chron File (alphabetical) (4 of 4), Oct-Dec 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1983 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jan-Jun 1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1983 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jan-Jun 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1983 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jul-Dec 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1983 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jul-Dec 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1984 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jan-Jun 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1984 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jan-Jun 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1984 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jul-Dec 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1984 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jul-Dec 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1985 Chron File (alphabetical), Jan-May 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1985 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jun-Dec 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1985 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jun-Dec 1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1986 Chron File (A-L) (1 of 2), Jan-Aug 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1986 Chron File (M-Z) (2 of 2), Jan-Aug 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1986 Chron File (alphabetical), Sep-Dec 1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1987 Chron File (alphabetical) (1 of 3), Jan-Mar 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1987 Chron File (alphabetical) (2 of 3), Apr-Aug 1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1987 Chron File (alphabetical) (3 of 3), Sep-Dec 1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1988 Chron File (alphabetical) (1 of 2), Jan-Jul 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1988 Chron File (alphabetical) (2 of 2), Aug-Dec 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1989 Chron File (alphabetical), Jan-Sep 1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)